Register of the Ekaterina Breshko-Breshkovskaia Miscellaneous papers, 1919-1931
Hoover Institution Archives
Ekaterina Breshko-Breshkovskaia Miscellaneous Papers,
1919-1931
XX011
Breshko-Breshkovskaia, Ekaterina Konstantinovna Verigo, 1844-1934
3 manuscript boxes, 5 envelopes (1.7 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, correspondence, biographical data, and photographs, relating to the life of E. Breshko-Breshkovskaia. Includes drafts of the book by E. Breshko-Breshkovskaia, The Hidden Springs of the Russian Revolution (Stanford University Press, 1931); a biographical sketch of E. Breshko-Breshkovskaia by Aleksandr Kerenskii; and three letters by E. Breshko-Breshkovskaia.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (3 reels).
Access Points
Revolutionaries--Russia; Russia; Soviet Union; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921; Kerensky, Aleksandr Fyodorovich, 1881-1970
BIOGRAHICAL NOTE
1844, January 13 Born, Vitebsk, Russia
1873 Began revolutionary activity
1874 Joined the Chaikovskii "To the People" Movement in St. Petersburg. Arrested and sentenced to five years of hard labor
1879 Exiled to Siberia
1896 Received permission to return to European Russia. Returned and was active in the Socialist-Revolutionary Party
1903 Participated in the International Socialist Congress in Amsterdam, The Netherlands
1903-1905 Travelled abroad
1905 Illegally returned to Russia
1908 Arrested and sentenced to lifetime exile in Siberia
1917 Freed from exile by the February Revolution
1921 Left Russia to live in emigration
1931 Author, Hidden Springs of the Russian Revolution
1934, September 12 Died, Prague, Czechoslovakia
Series Description
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1930-1934. (Box 1)
  Clippings, printed matter and reports relating to the life of E. Breshko-Breshovskaia
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1919-1929. (Box 1)
  Letters from and to E. Breshko-Breshkovskaia. Arranged alphabetically by name of corres-pondent
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1873-1931. (Boxes 1-3)
  Holographs and typescripts of E. Breshko-Breshkovskaia's speeches and writings. Arranged chronologically
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1930-1934
  - General (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Bell, T. H., obituary on E. Breshko-Breskovskaia, 1934 (Folder 2)
  - Kerensky, Alexander, "K. K. Breshkovskaia i Eia Druz'ia v Istorii Rossii," Paris, 1930. English translation included (Folder 3)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1919-1929
  - Unindentified letters, 1919 (Box 1., Folder 4)
  - Bell, T. H., 1929 (Folder 5)
  - Zubov, Petr, 1919 (Folder 6)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1873-1931
  - Autobiographical account, 1873-1878. Holograph. (Box 1., Folder 7)
  - "Obrashchenie k kooperatoram cherez tovarishcha Burygina v Tomske," n.d. Holograph (Folder 8)
  - "Zakliuchenie," n.d. Holograph (Folder 9)
  - "The Czecho-Slovaks in Russia," speech, New York. 1919 March 14. Typewritten photocopy (Folder 10)
  - Hidden Springs of the Russian Revolution, Stanford, 1931
    - General
      - Editor's Preface. Typescript (Folder 11)
      - Glossary of Russian words. Typescript (Folder 12)
    - Drafts and notes
      - Notes to various chapters. Typescript (Folder 13)
      - "The Historical Development of the Russian Re- volution." Typescript (Folder 14)
      - "The Intelligentsia." Typescript (Folder 15)
      - "The Peasantry." Holograph (Folder 16)
      - "The Religious Feeling of the Peasantry." Typescript (Folder 17)
      - "Revolution." Typescript (Folder 18)
      - "The Value of the 'To the People' Movement." Holograph and typescript (Folder 19)
      - "The Weak Points of the Russians." Holograph and typescript (Folder 20)
      - Untitled drafts. Typescripts (Folder 21)
      - Untitled drafts. Typescripts (Box 2., Folder 1-3)
      - Untitled fragments. Holographs and typescripts (Folder 4-5)
    - Typescript
      - Dedication. Includes holograph. (Folder 6)
      - Chapter I. "Kiev, 1873" (Folder 7)
      - Chapter II. "The Tschaikovski Groups, St. Petersburg, 1873" (Folder 8)
      - Chapter III. "Wanderings in the Ukraine" (Folder 9)
      - Chapter IV. "The Stundists" (Folder 10)
      - Chapter V. "Arrest" (Folder 11)
      - Chapter VI. "In the Prison of Bratzlav" (Folder 12)
      - Chapter VII. "The Prison at Kiev" (Folder 13)
      - Chapter VIII. "At the Soushtchev Police Station" (Folder 14)
      - Chapter IX. "The House for Preliminary Detention, 1875" (Folder 15)
      - Chapter X. "My Companions in the House for Pre- liminary Detention" (Folder 16)
      - Chapter XI. "The Fortress, 1876-1877" (Folder 17)
      - Chapter XII. "Preparation for the Trial" (Folder 18)
      - Chapter XIII. "House for Preliminary Detention, 1877-78" (Folder 19)
      - Chapter XIV. "The Trial of the 193" (Folder 20)
      - Chapter XV. "Sentenced. Litovski Castle" (Folder 21)
      - Chapter XVI. "The Journey Out, 1878" (Box 3., Folder 1)
      - Chapter XVII. "Nether-Kara, 1878-79" (Folder 2)
      - Chapter XVIII. "Barguzin, 1879-1881" (Folder 3)
      - Chapter XIX. "Ivan Linev" (Folder 4)
      - Chapter XX. "Preparations for Escape, 1881" (Folder 5)
      - Chapter XXI. "The Escape, 1881" (Folder 6)
      - Chapter XXII. "The Capture, 1881" (Folder 7)
      - Chapter XXIII. "Spread of Revolutionary Ideas, 1881-1905" (Folder 8)
      - Chapter XXIV. "The Revolutions of 1905 and 1917" (Folder 9)
      - Chapter XXV. "The Intelligentsia" (Folder 10)
      - Chapter XXVI. "The Peasants (Folder 11)